Guide to the Victoria Ortiz papers, 1942-1999 and undated, bulk 1960-1990 RL.00979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Victoria Ortiz papers
1923-1999 and undated
1960-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ortiz, Victoria, 1942-
RL.00979
12.2 Linear Feet
19.0 linear feet; approx. 14,999 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is partially restricted. Selected materials are closed to use until 2050.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Victoria Ortiz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003 and 2005.
Biographical Note
Activist and author, currently on the faculty of the UC-Berkeley School of Law; daughter of Bobbye S. Ortiz.
Collection Overview
The Victoria Ortiz Papers span the years 1923 to 1999, with the majority of the papers dating from 1960 to 1990. The main collection (2003-0204) comprises materials separated from the Bobbye S. Ortiz Papers and consists of one series; the accession number 2003-0204 was assigned to this grouping. Viki Ortiz's political and intellectual interests can be gleaned from the topics in the Victoria Ortiz Subject Files Series, which has been divided into seven subseries to facilitate its use. The first three subseries contain newspaper and magazine articles, organizational materials, photographs, pamphlets, speeches, and reports related to Cuba, Mexico, and Latin America. Scholars of U.S. anticommunism and student movements in the 1960s may find of interest materials related to Ortiz's 1963 trip to Cuba, taken with 58 other college students in defiance of U.S. policy. Each subseries is organized alphabetically by topic or title.
The parallels and differences between Viki's and Bobbye's political interests are reflected in their subject files. Both maintained extensive collections of materials on international women's liberation; like her mother, Viki was most interested in the status of women in Latin American nations. Yet while they shared similar social values and political beliefs, Viki's interests often diverged from her mother's. Viki's general files reflect her involvement in International Year of the Woman activities and her interest in population control, as well as her interest in such topics as reproductive rights, family structure, and economic justice.
Viki's great interest in adoption and parenting grew out of her own experiences as a single adoptive parent of a Mexican-born child. The subseries on adoption and parenting includes newsletters and publications of organizations for single parents; research for a book on single adoptive parenting; and miscellaneous clippings, notes, and other materials on issues such as adoptive parenting, international adoption, and gay/lesbian parenting. These materials are arranged alphabetically by topic or title.
The final subseries contains Viki's extensive notes and other materials related to literature. This subseries is organized into coursework, general literature, and Latin American literature, and is arranged alphabetically therein.
The addition (2003-0066) consists primarily of professional and subject files documenting Ortiz's law career, writings, and feminist and social activism. Her work on the literature and women's issues of Latin America are particularly well-represented. Portions of this addition are closed to use until 2050.
Addition (05-024) (3759 items, 7.7 lin. ft.; dated 1923-1997 and n.d) comprises research materials pertaining to gender, women, and the law; artist Elizabeth Catlett; and experimentation with LSD by the U.S. military. Includes family documents about Camilo, Ortiz's adopted son; teaching materials; files from CUNY law school; correspondence, appointment calendars; videotapes; travel diaries; photographs, printed material; and ephemera. This addition is closed to use until 2050.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Mexico -- History -- 20th century; Latin America -- History -- 20th century; Latin Americanists -- United States; Latin America -- Social conditions; Gay and lesbian studies; Women's studies; Photographs; Feminism -- Latin America; Women in politics -- Latin America; Latin American literature; Women -- Latin America -- History; Feminists -- United States -- Political activity; Women -- Social conditions; Feminism; Feminism -- United States; Women's studies -- Latin America; Cuba -- History; Feminists -- United States; Adoption; Gay parents; Lesbian mothers; Intercountry adoption; Ortiz, Bobbye S.; Ortiz, Victoria, 1942-; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Accession 2003-0204: Subject files, 1961-1984 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of folders holding articles, reports, speeches, newsclippings, class notes, and various writings by Viki Ortiz and others. Organized into the following subseries: Cuba, Mexico, Latin America, International Women's Liberation, General, Adoption and Parenting, and Literature, which is further subdivided into three subseries. The organization of each subseries is explained under its title.
  - Cuba Subseries, 1961-1984 and undated
    An extensive series of publications, articles, speeches, writings (some by Viki Ortiz), and memorabilia related to the Cuban political and cultural scene primarily of the sixties and seventies. Also includes several maps of Cuba, Photographs, and materials related to Viki's 1963 trip to Cuba as part of a United States student group. Organized alphabetically by topic.
    - 1963 Trip -- Cuban newspaper clips (Box 1)
    - 1963 Trip -- Martin Nicolaus photo/text exhibit (Box 1)
    - 1963 Trip -- Memorabilia (Box 1)
    - 1963 Trip -- Student Committee for Travel to Cuba (Box 1)
    - 1963 Trip -- US Press, related materials (Box 1)
    - Agrarian reform, Carlos Rafael Rodriguez (Box 1)
    - Alarcón at U.N. (Box 1)
    - Alicia Alonso (Box 1)
    - Articles, Le Monde, 1974 Apr. 6-9, Alain-Marie Carron (Box 1)
    - Blacks (Box 1)
    - Book Reviews (Box 1)
    - Books -- Instituto Cubano del libro, catalogs (Box 1)
    - Books -- Premio Casa, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Canto Libre (Box 1)
    - Center for Cuban Studies (Box 2)
    - Children, Day Care (Box 2)
    - Chronologies (Box 2)
    - Cienfuegos, Camilo (Box 2)
    - Cuba for Beginners, Ruis, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Cuba in Transition, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Cuba Update, translations by VO, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Cuba's Social Revolution -- Frank McDonald, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Cuba Times, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Cultural Activity, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Education, 1964-1971 and undated (Box 2)
    - Education -- FEU Alma Mater, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Education -- FEU statements, [ca. 1968](re: Vietnam) (Box 2)
    - Exiles (Box 2)
    - Exiles -- NY Times Magazine, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Fidel (Box 2)
    - Fidel -- conversation with U Thant, UN Secretary General (Box 2)
    - Fidel -- Speeches-- 1973 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Fidel -- Speeches -- 1963 July 26 (Box 2)
    - Fidel -- Speeches -- 1971 Apr. 30 (Education and Culture) (Box 2)
    - Fidel -- Speeches -- 1973 July 26 (Box 2)
    - Film (Box 2)
    - First and Second Declarations of Havana, 1960, 1962, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Flag (Box 2)
    - Folkloric Ballet, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Gaceta de Cuba, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - General Outlines (Box 2)
    - General Pictures (Box 2)
    - Guevara -- Man and Socialism, [ca. 1961] (Box 3)
    - Guevara -- reviews of Che's Reminiscences (Box 3)
    - Guevara -- The Role of Foreign Aid in the Development of Cuba, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Che Guevara -- Speech to UN, 1964 Dec. 11 (Box 3)
    - Health and Medicine (Box 3)
    - The Hemisphere, Relations -- OAS (clipping, 1974) (Box 3)
    - History ( Cuba, 100 years of Struggle, 1971) (Box 3)
    - History -- Casa de las Américas (Box 3)
    - Housing ( Cuba Review, 1975) (Box 3)
    - Imperialism -- Boorstein, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Important Figures (people) (Box 3)
    - "Land and People of Cuba" (by VO, 1973) (Box 3)
    - Law (Box 3)
    - Lecuona (biography) (Box 3)
    - Literature (Box 3)
    - Literature and Revolution, R. Salper, 1970) (Box 3)
    - Map (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 3)
    - Missile Crisis (Box 3)
    - Monthly Review Cuba Tour, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Outline, Notes for "Land and People of Cuba" (Box 3)
    - Padilla case (Box 3)
    - Photographs (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Pictures and texts (Box 3)
    - Playa Girón, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Poder Popular -- Center for Cuban Studies Newsletter, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Poetry, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Political Documents, 1962-1963 (speeches by Castro and Raul Roa) (Box 3)
    - Post-Revolutionary Cuba (Box 3)
    - Post-Revolutionary Cuba -- Jack Scott, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Post-Revolutionary Cuba -- letter about (Box 4)
    - Pre-Revolution (one clipping -- fragile) (Box 4)
    - Prisons (Box 4)
    - Rationing (Box 4)
    - Religion (Box 4)
    - Resource Information (Box 4)
    - Return to Cuba, H. L. Matthews, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Revista de la Universidad de Mexico, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Revolucion Mexicana, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Rodriguez (Carlos Rafael) interview, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Santería (Box 4)
    - Sintesis de Cuba, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Sobre El Partido, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Tainos (Box 4)
    - Travel ban, [ca. 1964] (Box 4)
    - United Nations and Cuba (Box 4)
    - United States and Cuba (Box 4)
    - Venceremos Brigade, 1974 (Box 4)
    - WBAI 1972 April, Cuba issue (Box 4)
    - Women (Box 4)
    - Women in Cuba -- Laura Punnett, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Worker's Democracy (Box 4)
  - Mexico Subseries, [1970s]-[1980s] and undated
    Chiefly articles, clippings, reports, and writings concerning the general politics and culture of Mexico in the twentieth century. The notes were taken by Viki Ortiz on a number of readings relating to Mexico. Contains few periodicals. Organized alphabetically by folder topic.
    - Amezcua Archive (Box 4)
    - Anti-Revolutionary Sentiment (Box 4)
    - Archive at Vnam (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Convention at Aguascalientes (Box 4)
    - De la Barra (Box 4)
    - Demographics (Box 4)
    - General Data -- history, geography, population (Box 4)
    - Huerta (Box 4)
    - Mexican Revolution (Box 4)
    - Mexico Today / Revolutionary Mexico (Box 4)
    - Morelos (state) (Box 4)
    - Notes on Anita Brenner's The Wind That Swept Mexico> (Box 4)
    - Notes on Soto y Gama La Revolucion Agraria... (Box 4)
    - Notes on Lesley Byrd Simpson's Many Mexicos (Box 4)
    - Notes on John Womack's Zapata: the Mexican Revolution (Box 4)
    - Outlines (Box 4)
    - Political Comics (Box 4)
    - Pro-Revolutionary Sentiment (Box 4)
    - Research Notes (Box 5)
    - Revolutionary Mexico (Box 5)
    - Solidaridad, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Things to Follow Up (bibliography, articles, interviews, etc.) (Box 5)
    - U.S. Involvement (Box 5)
    - Zapata (Box 5)
    - Zapata and Revolution in Popular Song (Box 5)
  - Latin America Subseries, [1970s]-[1980s] and undated
    Chiefly articles, clippings, reports, and writings concerning the general politics and culture of Central American countries, particularly of El Salvador and Nicaragua, and the South American countries of Chile and Bolivia. Contains few periodicals. Organized alphabetically by folder topic.
    - Bolivia (Box 5)
    - Central America (Box 5)
    - Chile -- Health (Box 5)
    - Chile -- Jardin Infantil (Box 5)
    - Chile -- report on psychological effects on victims of political abuses in Pinochet regime, 1978 (Box 5)
    - El Salvador (Box 5)
    - El Salvador -- Charlie Clements, M.D. (Box 5)
    - Nicaragua -- Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - International Women's Liberation Subseries, 1954-1979and undated
    Folders containing articles, clippings, reports, and publications relating to a broad range of women's issues. The largest grouping of folders is found under the heading for Mexico. Organized alphabetically by country.
    - Africa, Asia, Australia (Box 5A)
    - Canada (Box 5A)
    - Chile (Box 5A)
    - Chile -- Violeta Parra (Box 5A)
    - China (Box 5A)
    - Colombia (Box 5A)
    - Cuba (Box 5A)
    - Cuba -- Codigo de familia, 1975 (Box 5A)
    - El Salvador (Box 5A)
    - Europe (Box 5A)
    - France (Box 5A)
    - France -- Simone de Beauvoir (Box 5A)
    - France -- George Sand (Box 5A)
    - Guatemala (Box 5A)
    - India -- Family Planning (Box 5A)
    - Iran (Box 5A)
    - Ireland (Box 5A)
    - Italy (Box 5A)
    - Latin America (Box 5A)
    - Latin America -- Bibliography, Women in Latin America (Box 5A)
    - Latin America -- Latin Women's Collective (Box 5A)
    - Mexico (Box 5A)
    - Mexico -- Family Planning (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Frida Kahlo (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Maria, Liberación del Pueblo, 1978, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Tina Modotti (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Movimiento de Liberación de la Mujer (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Lopez Portillo (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Punto Crítico, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Rosaura Revueltas (Box 6)
    - Mexico -- Women and Revolution (Box 6)
    - Middle East (Box 6)
    - Peru (Box 6)
    - Philippines (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico -- Family ( The Puerto Rican Family of Today, Mendez, 1954) (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico -- Notes and outline (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico -- Population control (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico -- Women ( Contemporary Puerto Rican Stories: Spotlight on Woman, VO, 1972) (Box 6)
    - Spain (Box 6)
    - USSR (Box 6)
    - US (Box 6)
    - US -- Biographies (Box 6)
    - US -- Texas, Women in the Texas Workforce..," 1979) (Box 6)
    - US -- Vietnam (Box 6)
  - General Subseries, 1969-1984 and undated
    Folders containing articles, newsclippings, reports, bibliographies, and notes on a variety of general topics, including many materials on parenting, population control, and reproductive rights. Several writings by Viki Ortiz appear in this subseries. Organized alphabetically by topic. A large group of periodicals is filed under "Publications," and therein by title.
    - Abortion (Box 6)
    - Anthropology of Women (Box 6)
    - Art and Politics (Box 6)
    - Bibliographies -- Women and Women's Movement (Box 6)
    - Birth Control (Box 6)
    - Black Women (Box 6)
    - "Building A Feminist Economic Program" (Roundtables), 1983 (Box 6)
    - Capitalism and Women (Box 6)
    - Chicanas (Box 6)
    - Crimes Against Women (Box 6)
    - Criminality (Box 6)
    - Culture (Box 6)
    - Day Care (Box 6)
    - Divorce (Box 6)
    - Domestic Violence (Box 6)
    - Education (Box 6)
    - Encyclopedias, Treatment of Women in (Box 6)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 6)
    - Family (Box 6)
    - Fatherhood (Box 6)
    - Health (Box 6)
    - History, Women in (Box 6)
    - Housework (Box 6)
    - International Working Women's Day, 1984 (Box 6)
    - International Year of the Woman (3 folders), 1975-1976 (Box 6)
    - International Year of the Woman -- Commercialization, 1975 (Box 6)
    - International Year of the Woman -- Mexico, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Language and Women (Box 6)
    - Liberation (Box 6)
    - Literature and Women (Box 7)
    - Machismo (Box 7)
    - Marriage (Box 7)
    - Marxism -- El marxismo, mariategui, y el movimiento femenino (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Clippings, notes, articles) (Box 7)
    - Motherhood (Box 7)
    - La mujer miembro del partido... (Box 7)
    - Music and Women -- Ms. Gazette, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Notas sobre moral revolucionaria (Box 7)
    - Notes and Book Excerpts (Box 7)
    - Police Women -- La mujer policia..., 1976 (Box 7)
    - Politics and Women (Box 7)
    - Population -- Clippings (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Clippings (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Concerned Demography, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- El desarrollo de la poblacion bajo el capitalismo (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Latin America (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Repression in Latin America (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Third World Women (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- Population Control in the Third World: Free Choice or Coercion?, VO (Box 7)
    - Population Control -- VO (Box 7)
    - Population Policies and Growth in Latin America, 1971 (Box 7)
    - Pornography (Box 7)
    - Poverty and Women (Box 7)
    - Prostitution (Box 7)
    - Publications -- Against the Grain, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Publications -- Casa de las Américas, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Publications -- City Star, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Publications -- Concerns, 1973, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Publications -- Excélsior, 1974, 1975, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- FPS: A Magazine of Youth Liberation, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Liberation News Service, 1974, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Marxism Today, 1973, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Ms., 1978 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Off Our Backs, 1973, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- On Our Way (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Ormiga, May 1981 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- The People's Health, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Radical Religion, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Research in Progress (MLA), 1973, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- The Second Cultural Revolution - And Why We Need It (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Time, 1972, Mar. 20 (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Voices of New Women (Box 8)
    - Publications -- Women's International League For Peace and Freedom, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Religion and Women (Box 8)
    - Revolution (Box 8)
    - Revolution -- Sheila Rowbotham (Box 8)
    - Science and Women (Box 8)
    - Sex Education (Box 8)
    - Socialism and Women -- August Bebel (Box 8)
    - Socialism -- Books (Box 8)
    - Socialist-Feminist Conference, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Socialist Countries (Box 8)
    - Sports (Box 8)
    - VO 1969 Paper on Women -- Women: An Oppressed Majority (Box 8)
    - Women in the Labor Force (Box 8)
    - Women's Studies (Box 8)
  - Adoption and Parenting Subseries, [ca. 1979]-1983 and undated
    These files of articles, newsletters, newsclippings, notes, and other materials reflect Viki Ortiz's intense interest in issues surrounding adoption, single parent families, and gay/lesbian parenting. Also documented in these files is her participation in local organizations in New York State and New Jersey, as well as her initial preparations for a book on adoption. Contains some folders of correspondence. Organized alphabetically by topic.
    - Adoption -- Clippings (Box 8)
    - Adoption -- Notes on Readings (Box 8)
    - Adoption -- Resources (Box 8)
    - Adoption Book -- Notes for VO's book (Box 8)
    - Adoption Book -- Proposals (Box 8)
    - Adoptive Parents Committee, Inc., Adoptalk (Box 8)
    - Adoptive Single Parents of N.J. (newsletter) (Box 9)
    - Child Care Directories (Box 9)
    - Child Rearing -- Anti-Nuke (Military Tax Objection) (Box 9)
    - Child Rearing -- Anti-Nuke Rally, 1982 June 12 (Box 9)
    - Child Rearing -- Health, Safety, Protection (Box 9)
    - Child Rearing -- Non-Sexist (Box 9)
    - Child Rearing -- Sex Education (Box 9)
    - Clippings, Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Committee for Single Adoptive Parents (Box 9)
    - Conception (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1979 Dec. 7, 1980 Jan. 28 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1982 Mar. 19 (Box 9)
    - Council on Adoptable Children (N.Y. COAC) (Box 9)
    - Family -- Clippings (Box 9)
    - Foster Care (Box 9)
    - Gay/Lesbian Adoption -- Clippings (Box 9)
    - Gay/Lesbian Newspapers (Box 9)
    - Gay/Lesbian Religion (Box 9)
    - Gay/Lesbian Writings (Box 9)
    - GIFT: Gathering International Families Together (Box 9)
    - Hispanic Children (Box 9)
    - International Adoption (Box 9)
    - North American Council on Adoptable Children (NACAC) (Box 9)
    - Notecards for VO Book Project (Box 9)
    - Older Parents (Box 9)
    - Parents, Resources for (Box 9)
    - Parent's Center, Single Parent Clearinghouse (Box 9)
    - Parents' Press (Box 9)
    - Parents' Resources (newsletter) (Box 9)
    - Pre-School Association of the West Side, Inc. (PAWS) (Box 9)
    - Publishers for Women Writers (Box 9)
    - Raíces, Hispanic Adoption Program, NY COAC., 1983 (Box 9)
    - Single Adoptive Parents -- Notebook files (Box 9)
    - Single Adoptive Parents -- Clips (Box 10)
    - Single Adoptive Parents -- Questionnaire, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Single Birth Mothers -- Clips (Box 10)
    - Single Parent -- Bibliography of Parenting Texts (Box 10)
    - Single Parent -- Clippings (Box 10)
    - Single Parent -- Support Groups (Box 10)
    - Single Parent Family Project (newsletter) (Box 10)
    - Single Parent Resource Center, San Francisco (information) (Box 10)
    - Single Parenting -- Readings (Box 10)
    - SpeakOut!, Single Parent Family Project (Box 10)
    - Things To Do (Notes/checklist for adoption research), 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Voluntary Single Parents -- Names of (Box 10)
  - Literature, Classes Subseries, 1972-1974 and undated
    Class notes and writings from Viki Ortiz's coursework in the Graduate School, Comparative Literature, at City University of New York (CUNY).
    - Brazilian poetry, Spring 1974 (Box 10)
    - European novel, Spring 1974 (Box 10)
    - Guillén, Nicolas (Box 10)
    - Guillén, Fall 1972 (notes) History of Literary Criticism I (Box 10)
    - History of Literary Criticism I -- Notes (Box 10)
    - History of Literary Criticism -- Paper (Box 10)
    - History of Literary Criticism II -- Notes (Box 10)
    - Huidobro, Vicente (Box 10)
    - Lazarillo de Tormes (Box 10)
    - Mallarmé (Box 10)
    - Social Forces in the Latin American Novel -- Notes (Box 10)
    - Symbolism in Latin American Literature, Fall 1972 (Box 10)
    - Theory and Methods of Comparative Literature, Spring 1973-- Notes (Box 10)
    - Theory and Methods -- Latin American Literature: A Comparatist's Delight, (Victoria Ortiz - VO) 1973 (Box 10)
    - Theory and Methods -- Class notebook (Box 10)
  - Literature, General Subseries, 1972-1974 and undated
    Class notes and other materials from Viki Ortiz's graduate school coursework in comparative literature at CUNY.
    - Baudelaire -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Black Poetry, Women (Box 11)
    - Cervantes (Box 11)
    - Chernyshevsky and Dostoyevsky (Box 11)
    - Fanon -- Black Skin, White Masks -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Film -- Course Study Guides (Box 11)
    - French Literature -- Middle Ages, Renaissance, 17th Century -- Notes (Box 11)
    - French Literature -- 19th Century -- Notes (Box 11)
    - French Literature -- 20th Century -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Gide, André -- Earthly Fruits (excerpts) (Box 11)
    - Oscar Lewis -- In New York... (Box 11)
    - Mallarmé (Box 11)
    - Malthus, Malthusianism, Neo-Malthusianism (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 11)
    - Molière -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Zola, Emile -- Le roman experimental (Box 11)
  - Literature, Latin American Subseries, 1972-1974 and undated
    Articles, reviews, writings, class notes, and other materials from Viki Ortiz's graduate school coursework in comparative literature at CUNY.
    - Asturias, Miguel Angel -- Articles (Box 11)
    - Benedetti, Mario -- Articles (Box 11)
    - Best, Zoe -- Poems (Box 11)
    - Bibliography of Latin American Works (Box 11)
    - Borges, Jorge Luis -- Articles (Box 11)
    - Cabrera Infante -- Article (Box 11)
    - Callado -- Articles (Box 11)
    - Cardenal, Ernesto (Box 11)
    - Carpentier, Alejo -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Carpentier, Alejo -- Articles (Box 11)
    - Carrero, Jaime -- Poetry (Box 11)
    - Cesaire, Aimé -- Poetry (Box 11)
    - Cesaire, Aimé -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Chicano Literature -- Los Comanches (play) (Box 11)
    - Chicana Poetry (Box 11)
    - Cortázar -- Articles (Box 11)